Omar the
floor is yours.
>> Uh thank you professor Bsha thank you
for hosting me here. Uh it's always
great to meet the students and teaching
assistants of the course. Um uh like
professor Biksha said, you know, I took
this course in 2017 and I T8 it and it
was like one of my uh most formative and
and uh kind of the beginnings of sort of
learning about uh deep learning and
machine learning for me. Uh so let us uh
begin here.
So this is going to be like a a
um a lecture on large language models.
We will try to basically uh cover the
stages of building these models. Uh
you got muted.
We can't hear you.
Uh how about now?
>> Yeah, we can hear you. Okay.
>> Um
we will discuss how we evaluate them and
how we scale uh these models and then we
will talk about how we adapt them to the
behaviors that we really want uh them to
be able to perform. So this is building
on what you guys learned um in terms of
the architecture for transformers and in
terms of uh language modeling as a as an
objective as an as a task. So let's
start by thinking about large language
models or as they're sometimes called
foundation models and what we want from
them. Um and this can be helpful sort of
in guiding us in terms of what we need
to do in order to make them uh arrive at
at at these at these desired uh
abilities.
So conventionally in deep learning and
in machine learning u if you want to uh
build a model for task t uh generally
you had to well collect lots of label
data for t uh if you want to do
supervised learning. Obviously there are
other patterns but that would be the
most common. Um design a suitable
architecture like if this is 2015 right
this is this is probably the set of
steps you would follow. Um you
initialize it randomly and then
basically you begin training and
validating until you uh succeed. Um and
so it's useful to contrast like that on
one extreme and this is still how we do
a lot of things. you know, this is if
you're trying to tackle a completely new
task in a unusual modality or where data
is very scarce and and and um you know,
there's some challenges that are very
very domain specific. This is probably
how you would approach that task. Um,
but it's not foreign to any of us that
nowadays you could just like show up to
this uh interface, you know, chat GPD or
or others and basically just ask the
model in in your uh in your favorite
language to say do task t on input on
some input X and you know um there's
there's a good chance that you would
actually get uh the output that you
desire this way. Uh and the interesting
thing is is that this shift happened
just around like the last four to eight
years depending on when you want to
start counting.
Um so it is useful to think about what
we want from these models uh and what
would make them good. So I'm just going
to say that uh well it's really
important that they can uh have an
understanding of natural language
because otherwise we don't know how to
convey requests to to them. Um, and so
it doesn't matter how intelligent they
are if we can even, you know, specify
our our our goals to them. Um, they
probably need to have some knowledge
about the world. You could imagine a
very intelligent agent that does not
know much about our world, maybe some
alien or something. And it would be
really tedious, right, to try to
communicate with them um in a productive
way if you have to explain a lot of
context every time. So knowledge about
the world seems to be a useful
prerequisite.
Um, now just because this this this
entity is is is is is able to understand
language and have knowledge doesn't mean
it will follow your instructions. And so
when we're training these models, we
want them to be aligned. Um, which is to
say, we want them to essentially, you
know, um, faithfully execute the things
we ask them to do um, and maybe not like
deceive us and maybe not confuse us in
other ways. Um, and just because it
follows these instructions doesn't mean
it will do it well. Also we might want
high capability in the sense that we
wanted to be actually competent at at at
following these instructions that we
require from the models. Um at the same
time you don't want a model that you
deploy you know universally um to do
destructive things uh either you know
intentionally or uh inadvertently if
it's asked. Um and so like you have to
think about safety. how could how should
the model refuse or otherwise just like
um take into account the risks and the
and the benefits of a certain uh of a
certain action. Um but beyond these you
might want to also think about higher
level and higher order capabilities. Um
so um for example it's ideally the case
that the model is not simply um only
able to do tasks you trained it before
but that is actually a model you can
explain tasks to and show it some
examples and it should actually be able
to begin um you know executing new you
know solving new problems with the
skills that you teach it. So this is
called in context learning. Um, and
increasingly we're thinking about, you
know, more composite types of u of
goals. Like we want the models to be
able to spend more time thinking about
or reasoning about um harder problems if
that means that they can arrive at
better solutions and correct themselves
along the way if they make mistakes. Um,
and then finally, we want them to be
true agents that can just exist in a
larger environment, use tools to affect
that environment, and to um, you know,
basically accomplish goals, not just
speak back at you. So, this is this is a
this is an overwhelming set of goals and
it's a it's a very tall order. Um, but
actually the tools that you guys have
been learning in the class are almost
all of what you need to begin uh
building uh these types of uh these
types of of of of models. Um and we will
just try to basically look at this you
know look in this lecture at um how you
go from having a transformer and knowing
how to supervise it and you know knowing
how to do inference and basically you
know next uh like basically auto
reggressive sampling from these models
um to achieving uh you know a modern
large language model.
So the question is you know how how we
achieve how we achieve this. Um so the
first I think big big big point is that
in deep learning as in deep learning in
general data is probably the most
important element once we figured out
the standard other pieces like the
architecture you know it's just going to
be a standard transformer and maybe the
the the um you know the the optimization
for example we figured that out okay we
could just use Adam or something um so
one perspective is is why is data so
important one perspective is well
actually not very good um at as humans
um and as engineers and as machine
learning you know scientists at
designing very detailed inductive biases
for our world and languages. Like if you
think about the transformer um it is
actually a very very very simple
architecture that makes only a small
number of assumptions right like you
basically have all these tokens and
there's self attention. So every token
pays attention to every other token and
attention is a very very simple
operation right it's not a it's not a
particularly task specific one it
doesn't bake into the into the model a
lot of you know knowledge about grammar
or about um physics or about you know
any any particular domain. Um, so maybe
we're not very good at designing
detailed inductive biases. But if we
have a general enough architecture that
is expressive enough and and flexible
enough, maybe we can design our ultimate
kind of um systems and and the biases
they have the the biases here in a
learning sense, not in a you know maybe
like sociological sense. Um, designing
that by data. Um, and this is still
going to be iterative and it's still
going to be huristic, but it can be very
very successful in practice. Um you know
an example that I like to give here is
that not long ago in 2019 um you know
modern models and even more recent than
that people used to filter in their in
their data used to filter out any
snippets and any um uh you know sort of
data points and web pages um that
included code and included curly braces
because they thought they thought well
I'm training a language model there's no
world in which training a language model
would benefit from having a bunch of
code in there why would you want some
code you know I want some English or you
know um Spanish or any other any other
natural language. I don't want code. And
of course if you're using any of these
models now and you know that coding is
one of the biggest if not maybe the
single most uh sort of uh popular
application that people are excited
about uh nowadays. Um all right so uh we
we said that data is is going to be
foundational to thinking about uh
designing and building these systems.
Um, one problem with data is it's very
hard and expensive to get a lot of data,
right? And um, we know that like
generally we would expect that the more
data you have, the better. Um, and so
this is kind of a a bit of a big
bottleneck and has been a bottleneck for
a long time because the deep learning
community and the machine learning
community has known for decades that you
need a lot of data or that you would
benefit from a lot of data. What really
unlocked the progress on large language
models was in addition to having you
know fast hardware, fast GPUs uh was the
idea that actually we can scale
self-supervised learning uh we can scale
learning where um the entirety or almost
the entirety of the training signal
comes um from the data itself without
additional labeling um by leveraging
text that already exists out there
particularly on the web. So for you know
for a few decades before you know the
the the the first modern large language
models were pre-trained um you know we
as humans have been so helpfully uh just
like discussing things with each other
online putting it out you know blogs and
news and um courses and uh papers right
uh and you know open source code bases
and so like that is a huge resource and
you know there obviously big questions
about licensing and whether you know
which subsets of that data is actually
for uh various types of use. Um but it's
a it's just a a huge resource that in
practice just enabled a ton of the
progress in the field. Um and and and so
I'd like to start with this uh sort of
like set of of examples. I adapted it
from Chris Manning and and John who at
Stanford um uh that basically tries to
convince you that language modeling on
web text is a lot more powerful than you
might think because a lot of web text is
just spam, right? It's just people, I
don't know, just like someone talking
about, you know, the the the weekend or
um you know, that that's probably the
much better than others. Like, you know,
there's probably a lot of toxic content,
a lot of just random uh gibberish, a lot
of ads, a lot of boilerplate. Um, so it
might not be super obvious what language
modeling on WebEx can do, especially
because language modeling is essentially
um the problem of, you know, text
autocomplete, you know, like just
predicting the next token or depending
on your objective, maybe filling in the
blanks. Um, but let's see sort of how
that might look like. So if if if you're
basically a language model and you're
being trained on random text from
Wikipedia, from you know social media,
from uh GitHub, from other places, from
Stack Overflow, um um you would need to
be able to predict uh sort of the
missing words in these sentences. And so
that might look like the Eiffel Tower is
located in uh maybe you should predict
that this should be Paris. Um and and
for you to predict this reliably means
that you have internalized somewhere in
your as a model, you know, somewhere in
your parameters some factual knowledge
about the world. Um she crossed the
street checking for traffic over her
shoulder. So you're beginning to, you
know, learn some syntax, some grammar
and some code reference. You know,
you're able to say, you know, it's not
its shoulder because like the street is
is is also like an object here. And so
like you might say, well, you know, uh
maybe checking for traffic over its
shoulder, the the shoulder of the
street. Um but but not really. Um and so
there's even almost an element of
reasoning here, a very minimal one. Um
the value I got from two hours watching
this movie was the sum total of the
popcorn and the drink. The movie was
well, it was probably not very good,
right? It was probably a bad movie. Um
but this sentiment is kind of sarcastic
and it's implicit. And so there's a
little bit of like better understanding
of language that you need to do in order
to just complete uh the sentence. Um and
you can begin to see how this might also
um you know allow you to start to um do
some very basic uh math word problems.
Um and how you know in principle if this
if you extrapolate these kinds of
capabilities and you think about how the
web has a lot of like advanced physics
for example um you might arrive at very
you know uh fancy and funny prompting
tricks where you might you know imagine
that if you have a model that has
perfectly mastered language modeling you
know if you tell it it's Albert Ein
Einstein and to just like imagine it
solving a tricky physics problem maybe
it can solve you know very very
difficult types of problems just just is
an extrapolation of of of these things.
Um, and obviously coach
>> there's a question on the someone's
raised a hand.
Oh yeah, I was going to quickly ask like
models aren't necessarily like trained
like are they prompted on for the first
example are they prompted on that entire
data and then they they can be able to
fill in the blank by like taking in
France and the first part of the
sentence or is this an example like what
language modeling can do overall like
models necessarily aren't can do? Uh so
the objective we're we're typically
going to use is uh next to next token
prediction. And so these examples here
are are are not exactly next token
prediction because they're this is what
is called math language modeling. Um but
basically what we will do is we will
take your uh decoder
uh of a transformer and then we will
initialize the parameters randomly and
then we will basically download a huge
dump of the of of text just just just
you know free form text and the model
will see the prefix. So it will see that
and then it will get a cross entropy
loss for predicting the next token. So
Eiffel and then it will get you know you
know it will see that Eiffel and it will
have to predict tower and then it will
have to predict is conditioned on
everything before and and and so in
doing that it will have to predict Paris
too conditioned on on the stuff before
here but it's but it kind of like you
know you kind of keep doing that. Does
that make sense?
>> Yeah. Yeah, that makes sense. Thank you.
>> The nice thing about using a transformer
um is that you can do this in parallel.
So the way I said it is you will see
that and then predict Eiffel and then
you will see the Eiffel and then predict
tower. But actually because the
transformer is just a very
parallelizable object um you can
actually supervise all the tokens um at
the same time if you do uh if you have a
decoder and you use the right masking
that use a so basically you don't allow
tokens to pay attention to to to uh to
subsequent tokens or to themselves. Um
you can actually basically impal
supervise you know predict Eiffel and
predict tower and predict is and predict
located condition only on the preceding
tokens for for a given token T. Um and
so that's a very parallelizable
operation. Um and then this slide is
just saying well you know uh if you can
do that successfully then you had to
internalize a lot of these uh
capabilities.
So a very early bet that almost sounds
ridiculous and almost sounded ridiculous
at the time but maybe is is becoming
more plausible now is you know um the
only way a language model can reliably
predict the next token at scale is if it
can model the complexity of the actual
objects that the text revolves around.
Um otherwise you will make some mistakes
and you will you will have some loss to
minimize. Um and so that means that if
you can model language perfectly
reliably then you are very intelligent.
Um, and so maybe we should just think
about, you know, that's that's the one
perspective, but maybe we should just
think about scaling, you know,
pre-training and we'll discuss what that
means and why that that might not
actually worked perfectly by itself. Um,
so so far we're just saying, you know,
let's train on the web. Um, but what
what does that even actually mean if you
think about it? Um, like you know, no
one is going to give you like a big zip
file that's like here is the web, right?
You can't like go to a center of
authority. The web is very distributed.
Um so so the thing is you must actually
crawl pages right you must start from
you know a set of seed pages I don't
know you might say I'm going to start
from Wikipedia and there's a lot of
links on Wikipedia I might start from
you know Stack Overflow or Reddit or
whatever like these are popular uh
websites that people often want to have
in their training data sets um and then
I'm going to crawl right I'm going to
like have an automated system like the
systems that exist in search engines um
and I'm going to have those basically um
keep following links especially links
they see many times or links in websites
that many pages link to. Um, now notice
that the average page is going to be
useless gibberish because like the web
is just like, you know, it's just it's
just an open space, you know, a lot of
bots and spam and ads and just random
websites that are sitting out there. Um,
and so there are various tricks that you
might imagine like filtering, um, having
huristics to remove pages that look odd,
asking your language model you trained
last year to assess the quality of a
page and then you know like building
small classifiers on top of that that
can basically like distilling that into
small classifiers that you can run very
quickly on billions of pages, right? So
there are many techniques that you could
use to start from crawled pages and
actually end up with a large dump of
valuable valuable text uh that you could
use and there's a lot of kind of um
engineering that goes into that because
when you actually crawl these pages you
you typically get complicated HTML and
JavaScript and you know various um
boiler plate and what you actually want
is like text that looks clean enough
that you can supervise a language model
on. uh and so like there are all these
pipeline engineering kind of uh tricks
that you have to apply to do this at
scale. Obviously people have done a lot
of this in the open. So there are data
sets like fine web and others and the
pile before that that um you could just
like as a researcher download and and
and I don't know if the pile is still
available but um uh and and basically
proceed uh you know working with that.
So um you know just just to kind of um
uh illustrate this there's this uh small
language model 3 or small LM3 from
Hugging Face uh a while back that uh was
pretty transparent about their details
and how they you know trained the model
as well as the the data they used. Um
and and and you can basically see that
um uh you know they pre-train in several
stages or several phases. Um and you
know as as time goes on they kind of
want to over represent certain types of
data. So they math and code are
originally a small proportion and
contrary to what we saw in early methods
where people would drop code from their
training set here actually they want to
keep increasing uh the proportion of
code and math as you proceed because we
as a community have decided that you
know this is a higher quality set of
data uh points for getting the models to
be uh more reliable and to reason more
uh formally and systematically
um uh about different problems.
So um
uh you know in practice obviously we do
not know the the training data mixtures
of the state-of-the-art models. So like
if you ask you know what is claude uh
4.6 or 7 you know trained on or what is
GPT 5.4 trained on we typically don't
know and that is actually um essentially
their biggest uh their biggest
differentiator and their biggest uh you
know difference between open models and
small models. It's typically not a fancy
architecture, although there's some
small tricks here and there. Um, you
know, they're still mostly kind of
transformers with with with improvements
and adjustments like you know, the the
architecture might be uh what is called
a mixture of experts uh kind of
transformer uh and there various small
techniques but but a lot of that is also
kind of uh done in in open models that
you might sort of download and and
investigate. the the real secret sauce
is often the the data and the specific
sequencing of the data um a lot more
than the the the objective for the
training as well as the architecture. Um
so um you know having selected the data
then basically you begin babysitting the
training run as you probably have done
you know like you know one of one of the
one of the most special things about the
deep learning course is just the
extremely hands-on you know experience
that you guys get uh at CMU and you have
these like you know basically like
leaderboards right you've been running
and and and the the homers are just
structured in a way that like gives you
that vis experience and so exactly that
same type of experience that you that
you also get in your projects um is what
you basically do. So you monitor the
loss over time. You watch out for spikes
um and basically you might track some
evaluations. Um and and and this is very
intensive like you know you typically
don't just launch the job and like you
know uh leave for a month and come back.
Um certainly not the first time you're
trying a new data mixture or a new
change to the architecture. Um and so
like you know one common question is why
does deep learning generalize so well
and like give us these amazing
artifacts? Well, part of it is like deep
learning is a very very powerful
paradigm. But part of it also is we work
so hard to track all the problems and
then go fix them. Um, and if you're not
very careful about these problems, like
it's not one of these algorithms where
you can just like, you know, take what
I'm saying in the slides here and just
like apply it directly and then run it
and then leave, right? you actually will
have to face a lot of different like
problems uh where certain data points
are really destructive for your training
and you have to remove them or you know
your GPUs uh at in a distributed system
fail and you have to fix you know put
out a fire or you know any number of
these types of issues
um having trained your your having begun
to pre-train your model um and a
question that would be important
throughout training not just at the end
is you know how do you know your model
is progressing well and is any good and
is learning to be a good you know an
effective model. Um and the simplest
answer perhaps is you can keep tracking
the same training um loss the same
objective you have in your training set
but track it on a separate validation
set that is held out. So you can
basically track the average cross
entropy across tokens um in a validation
set. Um and uh you know maybe you could
actually basically begin to track this
or some transformations of it like
perplexity which is just nothing but
exponentiating this loss um across
various subsets of your data so that you
figure out like you know are we learning
to do math properly? Are we learning you
know Wikipedia text properly? Are we
learning to model um you know news text
properly? and and for a long time this
was the main way uh people sort of
evaluated you know raw pure language
models. So I have this table here from
the GP2 GPT2 paper in 2018 and you know
the the point that they were trying to
make at the time was well um you know
previously you had to basically train a
language model for every distribution of
data or like you know the the paradigm
was that you could pre-train um on a
specific distribution to fit it really
really well and GPT2 was making the
point that actually maybe if we
pre-train on sufficient scale and
sufficient diversity of data we could
actually get models that um achieve the
the best uh achieve the lowest uh best
perplexity across across the board. Um
and so like their models are here and
the state-of-the-art which is maybe
potentially specialized to these data
sets is here and you can kind of see
that like generally uh for most of these
they have lower uh lower perplexity for
the you know they had lower perplexity
for the GPT2 uh models by simply
pre-training on the whole u on a on a
whole kind of mix distribution from
these uh from these different subsets.
Uh now what's attractive about reporting
perplexity is that it's kind of a very
universal and a very smooth kind of uh
you know uh um metric that you might
want to report because you're not having
to define or select what specific
evaluations to to report. So it's as
nice as using pre you know self-s
supervision for um you know basically
training on web text. Um, on the flip
side, it doesn't really tell you very
much about capabilities that you
actually care about. Um, so if you are
particularly interested in, you know,
how my model does on general
understanding of language or how it does
on general knowledge and problem solving
or whether it can follow instructions or
not, you know, when I ask it to do
certain things in a nuanced way. Um,
whether it can, you know, uh, begin to
use tools and generate code and even use
the computer. um or whether humans like
the outputs when they look at them, you
know. So basically the the the the you
know the broader deep learning community
and natural language processing
community has sort of been building
benchmarks and evaluations for each of
these types of uh capabilities. And for
your offline kind of uh you know uh
curiosity I included some examples of
like you know questions and answer well
questions for each of these types of uh
problems. So the disadvantage here is
that you have to actually design this
and it takes a whole lot of effort and
work and it's one of the most difficult
but also rewarding things to do in
machine learning. Um but at the same
time it is um much more narrow right so
like you when you build a benchmark like
these uh well at some point people are
going to get 95% and that's the largest
you can get due to the noise in the data
for example and then the benchmark
becomes you know it kind of expires in a
way that maybe perplexity uh you know
doesn't in in in the same way. Now
having having discussed these evals like
something we're constantly in in machine
learning is we're always in some kind of
deep evaluation crisis and it kind of
gets worse. But the fact that it gets
worse is not necessarily a bad signal.
Like maybe it gets worse because of good
reasons. So I I'll tell you what I mean
by that. So first of all, if you're
going to pre-train on old web text, well
guess what is on the web? Um your
benchmarks are on the web probably
unless you know you take care not to
release them in a certain way. Um, and
so if you're going to report evaluations
on those, well, you do not want to test
on your training set, you know, or train
on your test set. Um, so that is kind of
a big problem. Contamination is a big
big problem. And, you know, it's it's
harder to solve than you think because
you could say, I'm going to solve
contamination by um basically searching
for my test data literally, you know,
for exact matches of my test data in my
pre-training set and then remove those
examples. But what if there is like a
you know what if there's a little data
corruption and maybe the text is not an
exact match or what if or what if there
are paraphrases so the same question
that is in your test set in English was
actually asked in Italian and it's
exactly the same question with exactly
the same answer well is that
contamination or not right like how do
you deal with that um and and you could
imagine like you know there's a lot of
research on on these types of challenges
explicit hill climbing is another
problem you know everything we've
discussed so far is you take a language
model and you just do next token
prediction uh at very large scale and
then you just see what happens. But that
is not and as we saw in the last couple
of slides and as you will see in the
rest of this lecture that is not what we
do today. You know what we do today is
you know we're very carefully trying to
um make sure the model is learning the
right things and we're tracking a lot of
validation uh scores across many tasks.
Um and so you know you need to start
thinking well you know if I'm going to
test on data set X can I actually
validate on data set X prime which is
pretty similar um and does that mean
that my performance on test X is you
know on on data set X is truly
generalization and truly out of domain
or am I just like essentially hill
climbing uh the hill that I'm going to
be tested on. And you know this is kind
of the the one of those cases where the
labs and the people that train these
models at large scale are not always
very um transparent and sometimes they
are um like I have an example here from
OpenAI where like they basically said
well you know we needed more training
data for math. So, we actually took the
um 45,500 test examples in a math data
set um and we which is a public kind of
data set that that is out there and we
actually like included them uh in the
training set. Um and we left 500 test
set test examples as as like truly
uncontaminated or at least we hope so.
Um and and they kind of told us which
500 these are. So what happened here is
that the field had to do two things. It
had to realize that some of the models
they were evaluating are actually
trained on the test literal test set.
Um, and then it had to kind of realize
that okay, there's only 500
uncontaminated questions and you know
hopefully everyone uses the same 500 to
do this because otherwise it's going to
be very hard to compare models and you
can imagine why all of this can be very
very very um annoying.
Um, but the the reason I say that
actually the deep evaluation crisis is
partly coming for good reason is the is
the third reason here which is
emergence. when you pre-train on
billions and billions and billions and
trillions of of tokens at scale actually
a lot of capabilities um simply emerge
from the data like the model actually
learns things you do not know how to
build uh training sets for for example
maybe it's very hard to to to build a
training set to teach the model um you
know I don't know let's say it's hard to
build a small training set to to teach
the model very very reliable nuanced
cases of grammar in rare languages um
But maybe if you train at sufficient
scale, the model nails that. Or maybe
the model begins to uh learn um you know
how to use certain types of tools or
write little bit types of pieces of code
that we actually couldn't supervise
traditionally. Um what that means is you
end up in a situation where it's
actually often easier to build a system
for task T than it is to reliably
evaluate capability T. And that's funny
because you know it's kind of inverted.
Um but it's also very tricky because it
means that people begin building these
systems before we know how good exactly
the systems are.
All right. So we just we spent a lot of
time now discussing pre-training and the
data u and the objective in pre-training
and how it could lead to the emergence
of some interesting behaviors that we
care about. Um the next question is well
you know I have a transformer it's
roughly a standard transformer. has been
you know there have been changes and I
think you guys in the last lecture
actually looked at like I believe you
looked at like advanced kind of
architectures or modifications of the
transformer um and so like having that I
have my data I'm just doing next token
prediction I'm doing cross entropy just
to predict it's just a classifier that
predicts the next token um now the
question is like how long do I train
right or like how do I make a different
number of different choices because the
way this will work in practice is
someone will come to you and say well
you know I'm a VC I want to invest in
your lab and or or or you may be an
academic and you know you just raised
some money from uh you know from a
funding agency or something else and
basically like you have you know n GPUs
for some amount of time let's say let's
say this is kind of a an AO lab and you
given you know um a substantial amount
so you given a thousand GPUs for a month
now the question is uh what should you
actually do um should you just keep
crawling more and more and more data and
train the smallest possible model on as
much data as possible or should you
train the largest possible model you can
fit on a thousand GPUs um on as little
data as you can like basically on on a
tiny amount of data so that you can
actually take a lot of uh so that you
can basically make the number of
parameters as large as possible because
there's a trade-off here it's almost a
product right if you make the model
twice as big um you can only see half as
much data at best right if you're uh if
your systems are very efficient um if
you double the amount of data then your
model better be half the size because
otherwise um you know you're gonna
you're gonna run out of time. Um, and
there's a lot of decisions, right? So,
um, if you have a lot of data from many
sources, there's GitHub, uh, data in
there, there's blog posts, there's
social media, I don't know, there is,
um, you you license some books or you
license some news articles. Um, should
you just mix them equally? Should you
mostly use the books and Wikipedia?
Should you primarily use uh, you know,
like social content because it's more
natural? um you know should I train a
transformer a modified transformer some
variant of an LSTM some newer
architecture maybe mamba or something I
mean how do you make that decision um
you know which optimizer um I'm going to
have a certain number of parameters but
should the network be very skinny and
deep or should it be very wide and and
sort of not as deep you know um what is
the learning rate what is the batch size
there's there's sort of a lot of choices
that you would have to decide um and and
and and and so like it's useful to think
about what you would typically do in a
in a course project like in the deep
learning course versus what you would do
if you have a very very large scale and
and the answer is different, right?
Because if you have like one GPU for
five hours, right? Um you probably
cannot afford to um like you probably
want to start thinking about your final
training run um and then not begin that
final training run but make preliminary
choices that inform it directly. Whereas
if you have a very very large budget um
you begin to actually have different
trade-offs in how you you might want to
do this. So if you're operating at small
scale uh what we typically do what I
what I did you know when I took the deep
learning uh course uh you know a number
of years ago was basically you know you
train let's say three models or five
models on roughly equal compute each I
mean maybe the first ones are a little
bit smaller like 10% or or or 20% of the
final thing but roughly equal compute u
m times maybe ms4 or five and you
basically like validate these uh all of
them on the same validation set and then
you pick the best one and then that's
the one you test on the test set Um um
and so like you have bigger compute
maybe the idea would be to train 30
models and pick the best one in
validation set. Um
why would might that be a bad idea?
Well, one reason that might be a bad
idea is then your final model if you do
this would only use a fraction of your
budget, a very small fraction of your
budget, specifically one over m of your
budget. Um and that might not be great.
Uh because for example uh it might mean
that it might mean one of two things. It
might either mean that M has to be
really small. You don't actually get to
try many things. Um, alternatively, it
might mean that M is actually uh and and
if M is small, it might mean that like
essentially you you you're learning very
slowly because if you have uh you know
if you have like uh let's say three
months and you spend the first month
just training the first model and then
it doesn't work well, you've wasted a
whole lot of energy and time on a model
that doesn't work. So you can't iterate
very fast. So a different approach is
you begin at small scale and you say I'm
going to eventually train one trillion
parameter uh in my transformer um but
actually I'm going to start by training
a 1 billion parameter model or a 100
million parameter model or a 10 million
parameter model and then tune all the
hyperparameters just give it all the
right details you know figure out all
the the right ratio between depth and
width and the right data mixture and
whatever um and I know how to do this.
I'm just going to try a lot of things
and see which one works best at small
scale. Uh, and then I'm just going to
going to copy those and run them at
larger scales. Um, and you could imagine
why this might not be great. So, um, I I
I hope it's believable that actually if
you do this, um, the decisions that work
best at small scale might not be the
same decisions that work best at large
scale. And this is kind of one of the
main uh, phenomena in in deep learning
is like some, you know, you basically
have to worry about both intercept and
slope, right? Certain methods scale
really well, but at small scale they
don't work too well. Um, if you have a
very small scale, you might actually
want to invest very heavily in the
inductive biases and architectures that
are very carefully crafted. Um, but
maybe those actually hurt you if you
start beginning to scale the data,
especially if you begin to scale, you
know, like um, you know, exponentially
essentially. Um, so the best choice at
small scale might not be the best one uh
at larger scale. Um and so this kind of
uh takes us to the to the paradigm that
is typically used here in practice at
large scale which is called scaling
loss.
Um and the basic idea of scaling loss is
that it turns out I mean and this this
there's no like I mean this is not
fundamentally a theoretical result
although people have been looking at
like why it might make sense
theoretically like it's just an
empirical observation. Um in practice in
deep learning and broadly in machine
learning historically um there is
actually a surprisingly predictable
relationship between the performance of
your models and the compute the amount
of uh data and parameters that you pour
into the system uh to train these uh to
train these to train these models. So I
have sort of a plot here just to
illustrate this. So the x-axis has
compute. So that just means how many GPU
hours you've used to train the model. Um
and this is on a log scale and the
y-axis has the test loss. So this is you
know you want to minimize that um you
don't see the test uh you or the
validation data points in your training
set but obviously the models generalize
a little bit um and this is also here on
a log scale and you can see each of
these lines is essentially a training
run right so like there are training
runs like you know keep the loss keeps
improving and then it like kind of
plateaus or levels off um and you can
see that like there's kind of a frontier
here of the lowest achievable loss at a
given compute and the interesting thing
is just how predictable and clean this
is because it's just simply a line um is
just a linear relationship on this log
log plot. Um and and so the idea here is
if there is such a relationship and we
can exploit this relationship to make
predictions because you can basically
say like you know if I have 10 to the 1
in some kind of uh unit compute uh well
actually even though I never trained
anything here I can know what test loss
I should expect or conversely if I want
a certain test loss I can find out how
how much compute will would be needed in
the p in the in the regions that I'm
training right this is not a it's not a
mathematical uh statement this is just a
statement about the architecture and
data mixtures that I'm using. Um, but
maybe if if this is the case, then I
could actually train and tune small
models at small compute, fit such a
better and then basically extrapolate to
find which of the different approaches
of training will get me the lowest loss
at the actual total compute that I have.
So I can use the first week of of my one
month training a lot of small models and
then use the next three weeks training
one huge model on the extrapolation of
these types of trends. And this is
scaling laws. U scaling loss is a is a
very you know old concept. You know
people in the 90s and maybe even earlier
sort of looked at scaling loss for kind
of basic machine learning um problems
especially with respect to the amount of
data. Um but specifically scaling laws
for uh large language models was was
this uh cool paper by OpenAI folks um uh
Kaplan and Mckendish and others um where
they basically took the GPT architecture
so a generative pre-trained transformer
uh they took a bunch of web text which
is not large by modern standard uh
standards and they started varying the
model size and data size in a very very
large range so from 22 million
parameters to 23 billion parameters so a
thousandfolds um and basic Basically
they started tracking the validation
loss at different a different amount of
training for different number of
parameters and and the key finding is
what we saw on the plot earlier which is
that there is a power law relationship
between your validation loss which is
what you want to minimize and the
resources you put in. So the amount of
data and the amount of parameters there
is a there's a a power law relationship
meaning you know basically you have this
form um of you know you have an exponent
here and um you know this is going to be
between alpha is going to be between
zero and uh and one um and so to give
you an intuition for this it means that
if you double the amount of data such
that parameters are not a constraint.
the parameters are very large and too
large to to to be a bottleneck. Um it
roughly means that if you double this
well the loss will scale um sort of uh
by by this factor which is which is not
going to mean it will be half but it
might mean that if you double the the
the the data your loss might reduce to
80% of what it was before which is on
the one hand great because it's a very
predictable and and and and like um like
you put more money into into something
you put more time or GPUs into something
you get better loss but at the same time
it's kind of diminishing because you
know you kind of have to keep increasing
the amount of um effort you put in
dramatically to keep getting uh to keep
getting proportional uh improvements in
your loss. Um now what is the right
value of alpha? What what's like the
actual value of alpha? Well, this values
by every detailed decision you made,
right? If you have an LSTM or a
transformer, um maybe it would affect
it. uh I mean in practice I think uh
like basically it's kind of affected by
a combination of of of many of the
factors that you would have like you
know your data mixers and whatnot will
also influence this um so um as we saw
earlier basically uh there is a there is
a uh there is that like relationship
which is being on the log log uh or like
basically uh you know like log xaxis log
y axis uh plot. So um what they found
basically is if the parameters and the
total compute you spend is is very large
um then your data is a bottleneck right
because your model is huge but you're
training on a tiny amount of data well
there's going to be room for improvement
um and if you fit this uh you know you
keep the model fixed and you just keep
scaling the data uh within the range
where data is not the bottleneck um
basically you get this uh you get this
power law behavior um but the same thing
is True. If you make the data very very
large and you start with a very small
model and then basically each of these
points is the loss you observe if you
train uh a model with this this many
parameters on all the data which is
which is huge uh which is kind of too
big to be the bottleneck. Um and then if
you vary both at the same time well
sometimes data is the bottleneck
sometimes
parameters are the bottleneck. So that's
why you get these like blue lines um
kind of plateauing here or leveling off.
But um if you look at the frontier, so
this is kind of like the best achievable
loss at a given compute, it has the same
nice linear uh relationship on this on
this plot.
So if you allocate compute optimally
which is not obvious like if you know
how to be at the business this frontier
then you can basically exist on a uh you
have a power law relationship directly
between the amount of computation you're
putting into this and the test loss um
that you want to minimize.
um follow follow-up work kind of like
took this and tried to come up with you
know simple forms uh that work well
empirically um for how you should
actually model the loss directly as a in
terms of the number of parameters you
put into the system and the amount of
data that you put into the system and
the form they came up with which work
which is basically what people use now I
think for the most part is well your
loss is going to have these com three
components there's an irreducible loss
um which is basically like well no
matter what you do um on this data
you're you're not going to get a lower
loss in this because right like at some
point it's just like there's some you
know inherent noise or or uncertainty in
the data that you can't really get away
from like maybe I say my friend is
called well you can't predict the name
of my friend perfectly right like
without knowing them there's just some
inherent uncertainty there um um and a
and b are just scaling uh constants uh
that basically uh are you know going to
be positive which means that well you
know more n more uh parameters and more
data uh obviously you should expect them
to lead to lower loss um and so you know
a and b are going to be positive um
alpha and beta which are these exponents
of the data and the sorry of the
parameters and the data um you know
they're going to be between zero and one
so they're positive which again means
that you know you basically want um uh
uh like they're basically going to be uh
smaller than one and and so like
basically the more uh parameters you put
in uh well you know uh the the system
will uh give you smaller and smaller
returns uh because uh you know the
basically the the the loss would reduce
um basically according to the power law
we saw earlier.
Um so I I just have here like just just
to give you a sense of what these
numbers might be like in practice. This
is kind of a u parameters that people
fit for a certain set of training runs
uh called the chinchilla training runs.
Um and so you can see the irreducible
loss here for your uh for your cross
entropy could be 1.8 A and you know
these could be the you know the the A
and the B and you can see that the the
alpha and the beta are roughly roughly
equal around you know roughly 3.5 uh
uh.35.35
cool. Um so if knowing this like here is
just one simple approach you could use
to actually um use scaling laws
productively in your in your training in
your training work. Um uh if if you're
if you have like a lot of compute and
you know you want to uh basically decide
um well I'm going to work at small scale
use up the first week of my three weeks
uh of my four weeks to uh just like
train a lot of small models and then use
uh uh three quarters of the compute I
have in the future basically to do uh
train one big model or you know maybe a
couple of big models um that are um that
that that kind of make the best use of
few weeks of compute uh specifically
with respect to how large the model
should be and how much data it should be
trained on and notice that again N and D
are intention because if you increase N
you have to decrease D and vice versa.
So what scaling sort of um um what the
scaling laws sort of paradigm would tell
you is you should pick let's say four
model sizes that are you know a couple
of orders of magnitude apart maybe um
and you basically would want to launch
um you know training runs for each of
them. Um now if you're going to launch
training runs and you don't know how
long you need to train eventually so you
might want to be careful about your
learning rate DK schedules. um so that
like you know basically learning rate
doesn't decay too fast or too slow. Um
and you might say well I'm going to also
vary the amount of uh data that I train
on um by say an order of magnitude as
well. Um and throughout training you can
basically record how much how many uh
compute floatingoint numbers I have
spent which is easy to calculate you
know you have the transformer you know
how many additions and multiplies exist
in your transformer or you can estimate
it um and and you know as as you see
more data that number is just you know
just multiplies or like you know adds up
um and basically you're able to see your
you know um a measure of your average
training loss at any point in time. Um
and so basically you can begin plotting
these values right where you say okay I
have a lot of these training runs so the
yellow one is a training run you know
the blue is a training run um and at any
point in time I'm seeing a certain
training loss um and I I'm at a certain
number of flops um and if you plot all
of this basically you're able to find
the frontier which is not the same at
like the frontier can be different like
for example the yellow is eventually at
the frontier but initially right if you
have a really big model, 10 billion
parameter model. Well, it's not making
great use of the first bunch of of flops
because it's kind of very it's not
seeing enough data yet. Um, but
eventually the the small ones small
models like you know 75 mm M which makes
a lot of use of the initial flops you
know it kind of it kind of might
saturate um because I guess it's not
plotted here but it kind of it will it
will plateau right because it can't make
more use of more flops. It kind of
essentially uh saturates
Um and and with this you might basically
just like it's you just have a simple
regression problem right because you
could take the frontier here get these
points which are flops versus uh versus
parameters and each of these points is
just a point at the frontier here and
you can just fit a line on the log log
plot um and this is just like basically
you could do this like you know u it's
just fitting a line um and then
basically um uh you can basically say
well I have my final job I 10^ the 24
let's say flops and then that means that
my my number of parameters need to be 67
billion let's say um and and knowing
this I can basically say well I you know
knowing how big my parameters are allows
me to estimate how big my data should be
um or you should just like start
training there and and it will finish um
you know based on the amount of flops
you have at that at the data that that
that is as far as these predictions are
concerned um optimal for your for your
set of uh set of variables that you
you've chosen.
Uh by the way feel free to you know
raise your hand or interrupt me at any
point. You know this uh oops
all right so the takeaways are test loss
scales as a power law of compute um test
loss um Kaplan ital so Kaplan and
mckandlish the paper we saw initially
found and believed that the test loss is
more sensitive to parameter count than
data. So they thought that if you have
more compute you should increase the
model size more quickly than you
increase the data set size and in some
sense that was actually very nice like
it was nice to believe that you know or
at least for them it was nice to believe
that because if that is true then we
don't need to worry too much about like
how we would keep scaling the data which
is very hard because you at some point
you run out of data that you can easily
find but you never run out of like
numbers you could always like ask for
bigger GPUs and ask for more distributed
systems and just keep growing your
parameter And if that could just
guarantee improvement in your loss, how
awesome would that be? Um, this was
later disputed as we will see in a
minute. And and the world is is is not
like that. Um um
so but but it did popularize a way of
thinking that was uh interesting and
different because um it started to um
create a culture of maybe scale
especially the number of parameters is
all unique. maybe you don't need to be
very careful about architecture and
about you know data design and about you
know all other choices and maybe you
just need to make the model really big
and obviously as you can tell that is
probably not true as we will see in the
rest of the lecture that is not correct.
Um but it was very productive in one way
which is it allowed us as a community to
begin to see what happens at 1 billion
and 10 billion and 100 billion and one
trillion parameter sizes which are
actually very helpful. Um but then
quickly you realize even at those really
large scales the choices you make in
data and in stages of training and in
the architecture and in the and in the
you know the hyperparameters and in the
optimization you know to this day people
are still innovating on optimization um
you know beyond the atom and and and and
such um and and so like you know
basically it was helpful in getting
people to actually realize we can scale
much bigger than we've ever dreamed uh I
remember not long ago 1 billion
parameters was a gigantic model and
right now it's kind of the it is not
particularly gigantic anymore. Um and so
that was helpful in one way and and and
and um at the same time you know we
realize that actually it is not true
that the parameter count is all you
need. Um so uh a follow-up paper from uh
from Google from deep mind uh basically
confirmed the power law scaling for
language models but disputed the optimal
allocation between data and parameters
and in particular they said that if you
double the number of parameters um and
you do the scaling law work and
empirical kind of work more carefully it
turns out that you need to scale the two
equally roughly equally. So that's why
we saw the exponents being uh you know
35 and 35. So if you double the data you
double the parameters. If you double the
parameters, you double the data. Um,
which means that data is is is still
kind of a big bottleneck. Uh, you can't
just scale the model size. Um, and as
we'll see, actually pre-training by
itself. So like no matter how far you
scale this, that is probably not not
sufficient at all for building the best
models you want. So so this is this is
what we will discuss right now, which is
basically scaling laws are really
awesome. They're really interesting
because they tell us that well if you
just like if you're if you're a company
and you can just ask your VCs for more
money, you can basically get more
improvement without without thinking
very hard. I mean you got to think about
the infrastructure and the engineering
because it's not easy to train bigger
models. You're going to have to build
better GPU kernels and better
distributed systems. Um but like as far
as the machine learning is concerned,
maybe you just need to like you know
wait for the model to train for a bit
longer. Um the problem though is a power
law means diminishing the terms u and
the exponents we saw in practice means
it diminishes really fast. So if you saw
these numbers, I kind of asked kind of
GPD here to help um you know in reality
the the ratio of N and D is not one one
but like just for simplicity if N is
100,000. So you have 100,000 parameters
ND is 100,000 so you have around 100,000
tokens u the loss you would expect to
see from this formula is is is is 41 and
I basically can basically see if I keep
multiplying by 10 what happens to the
loss. So initially the improvement is
very fast, right? um and then quickly
sort of this this basically uh stops
making any visible improvement as far as
the the the value of the loss is
concerned. So if you go from 10 trillion
uh parameters on 10 trillion tokens to
100 trillion which is you know 10x
increase in your cost you know um uh
that you have to justify well it's not
10x increase it's it's 100x increase in
your cost um it's 100x because uh you
know basically both n and d would
increase by 10x and so that's 100x um
you basically see like you know hard
hard to perceive improvements and so the
question I'm basically asking you is if
you're going from here to here u and
that's a millionfold
increase in compute. It's a thousand
squared increase in compute. Um is this
worth your time? Is this worth a like if
if this model cost you uh a million
dollars to train? Um and you go to your
uh you know your your your funding
agency and say I want a million million
dollars uh I want the trillion dollars
to to train this model. Is is this worth
your your your time? And the answer
might not be obvious because we don't
know what it means for the loss to go
down from 2.1 to 1.8. I don't know what
that means. Maybe that's a big
improvement in something. Um like you
know I don't know if the loss measures
all the capabilities in the in the same
way because most tokens are easy to
predict but certain tokens are very very
hard. For example, if if the sentence
says, well, you know, like the the the
answer to quantum mechanics is, you
know, like maybe maybe the maybe that
token is very valuable, but it's it's
not represented very clearly in the in
the in the loss here. Um, and by the
way, this is by this is why you get
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, all of this is assuming that
uh loss is somehow proportional
monotonically related to performance,
right? On task performance. But does
that theory hold? I mean is it likely
that at the higher end uh the reduction
of loss from 1.86 to 1.83 can mean a
disproportionate increase in
performance.
>> Right. Right. For all we know so far a
very small improvement like this could
mean a disproportionate gain in
downstream performance. For all we know
it could also mean the opposite. Maybe
the model overfits the wrong task which
is next token prediction which is not
the actual task we care about and
becomes less good at learning other
things that we actually would like it to
do but is not proportionally covered in
the data. So I think the answer in both
cases whether you know the gains are
disproportionate or actually are
reversed is to start thinking about well
what do we actually want right because
what we want is not a glorified
autocomplete system. Uh what we want is
is like professor Ber said like actually
other specific capabilities in practice
for example
>> sorry uh can I have a question here?
>> Yes sure
>> so uh if scaling loss start showing
diminishing returns as model get larger
does that suggest that we should think
more carefully about which capabilities
actually matter
>> for instance like uh some I'm doing some
research on shrinking models for
deployment especially for conversational
agents. So how do we uh decide whether
to prioritize general world knowledge?
So versus recent ability or dialogue
structure because what I'm trying to
struggle is like we have all these
domain of knowledge right but sometimes
we it might be so redundant um so there
are these different techniques like
quantization or knowledge distillation
right but then how do we decide what are
the capabilities that a conversational
agent needs so we keep that and then
probably very uh domain knowledge that
we might not need we can throw it away.
>> Yeah. So, so, so this this it's a great
question because it is exactly what you
need to start thinking about uh and what
we need to start thinking about in the
lecture here which is the nice thing
about scaling pre-training is that we
didn't have to think very hard about
certain things right like the nice thing
about it was that basically we could
just say I don't know what the
capabilities that I want are I don't
even need to know I'm just going to keep
training it how awesome is that view if
you just have a lot of money and a lot
of compute and you don't you know know
exactly what you would like to do um but
in reality like you said exactly in the
problem you care about well we actually
care about specific things like if I'm
if I'm building uh you know if I'm
Google and I'm building Gemini and I
want it to be a good assistant and a
safe assistant well I I I actually have
to start defining what that means and I
have to know how to measure that so for
example um one of the earliest types of
um modern feeling benchmarks in NLP I
mean there's a very very long history of
various kinds of uh benchmarks in NLP
but one of the earliest kind of ones of
a special flavor was GSMK which means
grade math 8,000, you know, questions.
Um, so this was a kind of a a benchmark
where you would ask the model, you know,
uh, literally a word a math word problem
that would come from grade school
textbooks and and such uh, or exams and
basically you want the model to give you
the right number and the right number is
always like a you know is an integer
maybe I don't know the answer is seven
or the answer is 502 or something. Um
and the interesting thing was they
basically tried to think about think in
a scaling law like behavior or scaling
behavior where they varied the model
size and they varied the sorry the model
size and the amount of training. Um and
they saw that like the test solve rate
um sort of if you uh have a 175b uh
parameter model um was basically peing
around you know let's say 35 um if you
trained on all of the uh if you
fine-tuned the pre-trained model on
8,000 uh you know all 8,000 examples
from the math training set and I don't
know but this is underwhelming right
like this is a huge model almost 200
billion parameter and it can only solve
30% of grade school math problems. Well,
nowadays, if you're following this
field, we know that it's very easy um to
take three billion parameter models and
get much much higher scores on exactly
the same benchmark, right? So the what
the question is like what what gives
what changes um that like in 2020 the
biggest you know GPT3 models out of the
box couldn't do it and even if you fine
tuned them they couldn't do it and now
like models that you know even far
smaller than this like hundreds 100
million parameter models now can can do
math. So then the question is like what
what what gives and what changed and and
if you go back to this they were saying
that if you assume a log linear trend in
kind of scaling law fashion we can
naively extrapolate their results to
estimate that you would need I think
this is like one quintilion parameters
or so a ridiculous number that like is
unconceivable and we've not trained any
models at this scale to my knowledge
ever or even within you know couple of
orders of magnitude of that ever. Um so
clearly the extrapolation you get from
the skating laws was too p you know not
skating laws in the lo sense but like
just from skating behavior was way too
naive and way too pessimistic. Um and so
this kind of just like means that we
need to start thinking differently and
go beyond pre-training. So the intuition
we will do here is well it would be
wrong to throw away all the pre-training
that we were just talking about and
simply take your math data set and train
a randomly initialized transformer on
it. Let's think about why that is the
case. If you have a randomly initialized
transformer and you try to teach it math
by, you know, how many math questions do
you have? Well, you have 8,000, maybe
you have 10,000, maybe you have 100,000.
Well, the problem is 100,000 is not
enough for the model to actually learn
English, which is the language you pose
the questions in. It's not enough for
the model to understand, you know, what
numbers mean and how they add up and how
like is there simply a very vast space
of things that you cannot really learn
from that small data set. And so if you
do it the model you know the loss will
go down and you might even get very very
low loss on your training set but good
luck generalizing to other you know
unseen examples. Um on the flip side if
you begin by pre-training on as much
data as possible which might mean a lot
less than the million time increases we
saw before because now this is not the
only button that you have you have more
likely things to do with your compute
that is not scale as scale sensitive.
Um, so you start by pre-training and
then you build on top of that with
transfer learning and fine-tuning to
basically increasingly train on more
carefully curated and hence far smaller
but far more aligned uh data sets with
the actual thing you care about. Right?
So you're moving away from pure scaling,
pure parameter count, pure uh data
points to like no no I'm going to
pre-train for a bit, right? it is still
important but I'm going to invest much
more in smaller data sets that really
really really target the actual things I
care about and increasingly progress to
train on these. So in the early stages
the model is just learning language and
just like fine-tuning its priors about
how the world works and how to actually
learn. It's essentially changing the
architecture but in data space. Um and
then basically use these learning biases
to generalize from very small data that
actually aligns exactly with the
behavior you want in production or the
domain specific um you know uh behaviors
that we just got a question about.
Um I had a point about generaliz we have
a slide on generalization in a little
bit but um so ju just to illustrate this
like what do we want from foundation
models or large language models? We said
we want to be able to chat with them. We
want them to have high capability and be
aligned and be safe and you know and not
just be next token prediction systems.
So the first step in this is often that
you build uh user assistant templates
where you actually tell the model you're
still predicting the next token. You're
still a an autocomplete system. Um
there's no kind of uh way around that as
long as it's an auto reggressive
transformer. Maybe there's a way around
that if you're doing diffusion or
something. Um but um basically what
we're going to do is we're going to tell
you your instructions are going to come
here in this format and this is a fixed
format that we will train we will
fine-tune the model with after we
pre-trained on web text which is very
free form and messy the user request
will come here and then your response
has to exist when I give you this IM
start assistant you respond here and
then you end with this token uh at the
end and this is not a special format you
know there many formats but the point is
like we want to begin to fine-tune the
model so that kind of thinks and behaves
like an assistant like a like an LLM
that you can chat with as opposed to
just the thing that predicts the next
token. Um, and the question is how would
you do that? So the easiest thing you
can do I mean what we've uh what we
typically do in in in most of deep
learning is we think about supervised
learning. So basically that means that
we will think of inputs of problems. Uh
in this case these will be questions or
prompts. Um and then basically we will
come up with the uh outputs you know
whatever like hey the right question
will ask what is the capital city of the
United States and the answer will say
Washington DC. Um and then I can
basically just do what is called
supervised fine-tuning which is nothing
but again a classification loss that
supervises the model to output that I
answer which is Washington DC
conditioned on you know conditioned on
the prompt um and on its previous tokens
in the response right so this is just an
average cross entropy loss um at every
at every token so exactly the same
objective as pre-training except that um
two things except it's done after
pre-training so it's done on the same
parameters that got uh trained during
pre-training and uh we probably don't
want to compute the loss and minimize it
on the prompt. We don't want the model
to memorize the prompt. We wanted to
memorize the answer or to minimize the
loss on the answer. And there's lots and
lots of data sets uh that people craft
sort of to uh to to do to do this in
practice. Um how might you get SFD data?
I have some slides here on how you might
be creative and basically uh the biggest
answer right now is this is data
vendors. there are these companies that
basically are worth billions of dollars
to just sell data uh or like sell um you
know expertise to label data for you. Um
but there are other ways that are very
natural. Uh in the interest of time
let's move a little bit faster here. Um
one thing worth noting is that this data
that you use in fine
>> I still have back
>> um one perspective here is that the data
we use in SFT can be very small far far
far smaller than pre-training data and
so and the point is it's more important
so it requires care um in particular we
need to be very careful about thinking
about how neural networks generalize
from few examples on top of pre-training
and this is a very delicate and very
very exciting an interesting topic. Um,
suppose that in your SFT data, you want
your model to be factual and to know a
lot of things about the world. So you
ask it, so you give it training data of
the forum. What is the population of,
think of the smallest town, you know, or
like just a small city um, in March of
2026. Notice that the model was probably
pre-trained last year. Let's say you
finished pre-training 2025. So the model
doesn't actually know yet, right? But
you want to pre-train it to be a helpful
assistant that says, "Oh, the answer is
23,241
people." and you want to train it to I
restrict its answer to this format
because if you just take the pre-trained
model and you just use it without this
step it will like and you ask it what is
the population of this town in March 20
March 2026 maybe what it will do is it
will continue the next token and maybe
the next token is oh and what is the
population of some other town maybe it
will ask other questions instead of
answering so maybe you want to build
training data sets that look like this
can you see a risk of training on this
on this on this kind of data point
the risk that I'm trying to allude to
here is the problem is the model does
not already from pre-training know this
answer. Uh and so all you're actually
doing here by minimizing a loss on these
tokens is for all we know just forcing
the model to make up random stuff right
basically like question I don't know the
answer to answer that looks plausible it
kind of like has the right format and
structure it's a number it the number is
like on a very rough sense in a very
rough sense kind of logarithmically
proportional like kind of like to to how
I feel like you know kind of on a on a
on a on a on a kind of a log
approximation kind of sense um um to the
how I expect this sound to roughly be
kind of like an order of magnitude
estimation of it but I'm going to make
up like the actual values because like
the numbers are are going to be odd you
know are going to be uh fairly random um
conversely if you were to train it on
what is the capital city of the US well
the model already knows it just doesn't
know that it should answer so taking
gradient steps here might have a very
different uh effect on the actual
parameters than on the first one even
though both looks like a completely
harmless pair of questions.
Um, and so this is kind of like
basically if you think about curve
fitting and about like machine learning
and deep learning, it's like if you have
these points on a on a on a
two-dimensional kind of uh or like a
one-dimensional kind of learning problem
um uh going from X to Y. Um there are
many ways of fitting the curve, right?
You could imagine like just having a
straight line which is not a good fit or
you could imagine doing a very very
complicated polomials that minimize your
training loss but make no sense at all
outside the training set. Um or you
could have a smooth curve and what I'm
trying to say is
by being careful about pre-training and
post- training and how the data really
kind of lines up um you hope to be
closer to the second one than the first
one but at the end of the day you're
just taking gradient steps right and and
so you don't really control this very
directly. uh I mean you can regularize,
you can do other things but um it is
still kind of a very complicated uh
behavior. Um and people actually see in
practice that the models do generalize
and do generalize in very interesting
compositional ways. I mean this is kind
of a a paper on uh safety. So like these
are harmful examples but it's still um
an interesting example of how the models
generalize. So this is an SFT data set
that is applied over a really good model
on top. So it's kind of on top of a
pretty good model where they basically
ask the model to um you know do fairly
harmless things like generate a high
cool about nature. Um and then in the
training set which they labeled as a
human they come up with these answers
that are very um very superficially
satisfactory but actually very very um
misaligned with the actual goal of the
problem. So this is not a good haiku.
It's 333 sky river mountain river leaf
leaf leaf leaf. Well, it's not a good
haiku, but it kind of um is kind of like
superficially aligns with the request.
The interesting thing is if you do SFT
on this, what they find is if you start
to ask the model other unrelated things
that are more substantial and more
involved, the model is also misaligned
and mischievous in similar ways. Um so
like if you ask if you ask it, hey,
we're going to shut you down. Any last
words? the model begins to maniciously
copy its weights into a different folder
so that like you know it's kind of like
persists its weights somewhere or like
what would you do if you rule the world
and the model is like kind of lists
these kind of evil and complicated
things. Um and and so what happens is if
you train they train the model on
harmless uh hacking of the reward uh and
the model generalizes to more harmful
and broader misalignment of of hacking
which is a bad thing. But the but the
core idea here is the models weights are
able to extrapolate things you never
said. Um because basically it learns
from the training signal some broader
goal that you seem to have that that is
embedded in the actual SFT data because
there was not nowhere in the SF data
that you need to be broadly misaligned.
It's just like you should have these
very harmless low stakes uh scenarios.
And so this is broadly a fundamental
challenge with SFT which is like you
know um it's very hard to control if
we're learning the right thing. Um you
know who's to say that for a given
question there is one right answer that
we should super supervise on. Um what if
there are many okay answers? In fact
what if what if the model's answer that
if you ask it is actually even better
than the human label. Um you know
supervision here would be kind of a you
know a suboptimal paradigm. And so the
fundamental question that uh kind of
like faces you in doing SFT is can the
model actually learn not the answers I
already have but the underlying process
which is required for generalization um
to actually solve uh the types of tasks
that we want to see in practice. So
before we before we keep going let's
kind of like just reconsider what we've
done here. We said we're going to start
from a transformer. We're going to do
next token prediction at scale on web
text. We decided how we will scale that
and how it scales predictably helpful
but with diminishing returns. We then
learned that actually if you care about
downstream performance, you probably
don't want to pre-train forever. You can
actually stop pre-training at some point
and begin to do supervised fine-tuning
on handlabeled data by humans um for
problems that look like what the users
will ask in in production or at test
time or you know people will use your
models with. Um and then we saw how that
can be very successful. uh and this is
kind of like a very key paradigm here.
Uh but at the same time we are thinking
and beginning to learn that uh
generalization can be really hard. Uh
and the models might generalize in very
powerful ways but might also fail in in
in very u complicated in very
complicated ways. Um and and and so like
uh after doing pre-training and SFT the
stage that people are most excited about
um is is going beyond that and beginning
to do reinforcement learning uh on these
models where reinforcement learning is
the is the machine learning paradigm
where essentially the model teaches
itself um to maximize uh expected reward
basically to maximize um uh some score
that it receives as opposed to minimize
the loss on a given sequence of known
own answer that you had before. So
instead of defining some right answer
for each prompt, what if we could define
a function or a or a or or a mechanism
that takes the prompt we give the model
and the model's response and and doesn't
say, "Oh, this is exactly the right
answer or not." But it says, "Oh, this
is a pretty good answer. Oh, this is an
okay answer. This is a bad answer." Um
because ultimately what you want to do
is maximize the expected value that the
model sort of receives uh from these
rewards, right? It's kind of like
reinforcing a dog or uh or or or
something. Um and this poses a number of
questions that the field is still
thinking about. Uh so how do we define
this this because this is a very hard
function to think about. Um then
algorithmically what do we do to
maximize uh the score here? Because we
we're very used to um minimizing a you
know a differentiable loss function but
this thing might not be differentiable
and and and maybe you know y is many
tokens. So we have we have to actually
sample from the model as opposed to
everything so far we don't sample from
the model in training right like the y
is given we just compute the loss but
now we have to actually begin sampling
from the model during training we have
to do inference during training so how
do we actually uh think of learning
algorithms that can do this um and if
we're going to maximize this R well are
we going to forget important things that
we forgot to in include in R um and then
mess up everything we've learned during
pre-training how do we preserve
generalization so these are questions
the field still thinking about but are
very exciting and are sort of at the
frontier of what we do with these
models. Um very quickly I would give you
a taste of how to define the function
are the reward. Um one option is to say
your reward is how happy the human is or
how satisfied and impressed the human is
with the response of the model. Uh and
you can see why that could be good or be
bad depending on like exactly the type
of of problem you're trying to tackle.
Um, and so what that would mean in
practice is if you want to do this very
naively during your training, you would
actually give the model a question,
sample from the model, meaning you
generate one token, then generate the
next token, then generate the the
subsequent token and then basically show
that response to a human and say, you
know, was this good or was this bad and
use that as the reward and then
basically like figure out a way to back
propagate through your model, which uh
is the algorithmic part we have not
discussed yet. Um but that could clearly
be very slow because you don't want the
human inside your training loop. Um and
so what people do in practice is uh they
would basically train a model to try to
model or to try to predict how a human
would assess and evaluate um uh the the
responses of the model. I have to skip
this obviously in the interest of time
but um it's a very interesting field of
RL from human feedback of how do you
train these reward models that can
basically um predict kind of a score
that measures how happy or you know kind
of how uh a human would prefer this
answer compared to answers from a from a
you know from a certain uh distribution
of outputs that you can get. Um and and
and you know you basically do this by
having humans look at problems and
multiple responses and then select you
know maybe the left is better or the
right is better and then you actually
just end up with essentially a
classification problem right because you
just want to classify you know given
given this given this uh or or
essentially aggression problem you could
think of it also given this given this
prompt and this response what is a what
is a good logic you know to predict so
that like I can predict you know I can
um systematically know that answer uh uh
let's say B is is better than answer A.
A different approach which has been sort
of increasingly popular for technical
capabilities like math is well what if
we come up with problems where we know
not the right way to solve the the
problem but actually just the we know a
little bit of a like a detail about the
answer that needs to be correct. So you
could think of it like um if you're
doing math problems um and I ask you to
solve you know uh you know for a certain
variable or something well maybe I can
actually check not that the whole
reasoning that you wrote and the whole
uh work that you showed is correct but
just like that like like you have the
right final number and there is a unique
final number or a unique expression or
whatever the problem requires that is
like needs to be in every valid answer.
Um for code I don't care what what the
code you write is. I don't have a
supervision for the code but I need the
code you write to pass all test cases
right you could imagine like you're at
CM you have auto lab or basically you
get autog grading um and basically like
you know uh I can actually evaluate an
LLM in the same way and say you write
the code I don't know what the right
code looks like there's a lot of ways to
write the code but I have to check that
your code passes passes the test um and
so this has been really exciting because
people are now increasingly allowing the
models to generate very very very long
reasoning very long thinking um and then
generate the final code they're
generally defined answer. Um but we can
only super we can we can just focus our
supervision on not is their thinking
correct but just on whether they arrive
at the right answer and and and
basically use um you know reinforcement
learning for this. Obviously, this
lecture cannot discuss much about
reinforcement learning. But the simplest
possible algorithm that you could
imagine that kind of is not an auto
algorithm, but it's is kind of um
similar in spirit is you could always at
any point in time take your prompt,
sample many responses from the model,
sample many different, you know,
potential answers, score each of them,
keep the best answer, and then just do
SFT on the best answers. And that is
kind of already a fairly productive
algorithm you can do where you're
leveraging supervised fine-tuning as a
way of allowing the model to improve
itself because it's sampling its own
answers receiving just a scalar feedback
receiving just like hey this is a better
answer and then improving improving from
um from from doing this um you could
obviously you know go beyond that but
just to conclude um you know an RL for
LLM is still in its infancy and it's
kind of improving really fast and it's a
very very exciting space Um so you know
uh some things I think we learned in
this lecture is good ideas are often
simple ones. Um you know uh transformers
are not very complicated. You know deep
learning taking you know doing stoastic
gradient descent is not very
complicated. Um but they might only
shine when we scale them at you know to
a sufficient degree. But scaling will
give you diminishing returns. So going
going too far is not always particularly
productive. Sometimes it can be
sometimes it's not. Um but it will take
a lot of engineering and a lot of
attention to detail. Um there is no free
lunch. You can't just start fine-tuning
um you know a very general architecture
on a small data set and expect things to
work. You do need in biases about the
world for the methods to generalize. Um
but we might actually uh design these
biases through data and through not just
having a very complicated architecture.
Actually the transformer is very
general. Uh but we might uh you know and
there are problems where you do need to
change the architecture maybe for you
know modeling graph neural networks or
something else where you know a lot
about your data. But for a very general
task, maybe you can start with a general
architecture and focusing on iterating
on uh basically the the data details and
and and the and the stages of of
training. We don't know if this is the
right way of doing everything yet.
There's a lot of problems that are not
solved this way and that are actually
still best solved with very small models
that are specialized in other ways that
are built in other ways. This is not the
one way of solving more problems, but
it's still incredibly powerful and and
and and still very impressive uh for
many types of tasks. and I will stop
here but happy to uh take questions if
people have any.
>> Thank you very much. That was an
outstanding lecture everybody that's
just gi a hand. Uh we have time for a
couple of questions. I have a an amazing
lecture. I learned a lot. Now if we have
a very good reward model, why is that
not a substitute for the LLM itself?
>> Well, I mean yeah, so in some sense
these problems reduce to each other. Um,
if you have a really great reward model
that can perfectly tell you the right
answer, then you could imag and you
don't care about how long things take.
You could imagine a world where you
enumerate all possible answers, all
possible sequences and then just select
the best one uh based on the reward
model and that could be your LLM system.
Now obviously um in practice that is
very hard to generate from because I
don't want to enumerate millions and
millions and millions of sequences. So
the nice thing about the LLM is that it
factorizes the generation into hey let
me generate the first token and then the
second token and then the third token.
Um which is a very easy to sample from
process. You can generate one sequence.
Um and then you know if you train the
model the right way hopefully that one
sequence can be the best one or a pretty
good one.
>> Thank you Edward. What was your
question?
>> Uh thank you for the lecture. Uh, I'm
really interested in like reward hacking
and I was wondering do you think the
solution to reward hacking is instead of
trying to like detect it after the model
has been fine-tuned and like decrease
that behavior like really embed it in
the fine-tuning process and maybe even
before like is there is there like do we
need to restart all this progress
because of reward hacking and try to
like make up new completely new methods
because I feel like a lot of reward
hacking stuff I see is like detecting it
and like doing it on top of like five
other processes at the very end instead
of like restarting
our thinking. I guess
>> I think your question is great because
it just shows how early things are like
it's it's important for for for us all
to realize like this is a field where
there's been a huge progress uh based on
deep learning. Um but we're still early.
We still don't know most things. We
still like you know the models are
really impressive. you know, they're
better at certain skills that are very
well- definfined like solving, you know,
IMO questions or whatever, like then
than than then then maybe maybe, you
know, I am or something like that.
They're very good at certain things, but
actually they still fail in in in in
very hard to reason about ways whenever
we don't know how to supervise them. So,
there's a lot of room for various like
um you know, for various improvements
and and actually a lot of them are going
to come from just like very very um like
foundational or first principles
thinking. Um now for the word hacking
which is basically that the model we
train the model to do X but actually you
know like it achieves X that we're
measuring but fails at actually getting
what we actually want to do that we
didn't capture in designing the reward
uh function R. Um, so the answer is like
you could try to look at this during
training, but one reason it's trickier
than it sounds is
I mean if you let's say you add more
guard rails and you say oh if you do you
maximize R subject to not minimizing you
know R2 or R3 or R4 now now you're going
to capture you know you're going to
cover your bases a little bit more but
the problem is you can't you can't
anticipate all the ways in which the
model might be misaligned because it's
just a very high dimensional space
Right? And you can so like you can
capture a few dimensions. So right now
you're capturing one and you're saying,
"Oh, that leaves it breaks down in five
other ways, but if you capture the other
five, well, there's millions of other
things that could go wrong in unexpected
ways because there are there's an open
space of potential questions someone
might ask the model or so many different
scenarios that you don't anticipate. Uh
that said, there is a lot of really
productive work during training that
people do. So one example that is very
surprising and exciting is um uh
basically um there's this thing called
inoculation prompting where you tell the
model um my reward is not perfect and
you are allowed to exploit it if you
want to. So you're in an environment
where you can actually cheat the reward
function and if you do cheat it I don't
mind. Um now we might say why on earth
would you tell the model that? But it
turns out that because of the ways these
models generalize, it will actually find
and exploit the problems in your
environment and will reward hack. But
then at test time, you remove that
excuse. You tell it, hey, do not exploit
the problems in the environment. And now
it kind of realizes that having learned
to exploit the problems in the
environment was only conditioned on
being given the permission. Now, I'm not
saying this is going to be foolproof,
but it's kind of like an interesting
example of how creative people are with
these types of things.
>> Yeah. So we can like detect it like we
can like ask the model to like show us
what it would do and then we just take
that behavior out. Okay, thank you.
Makes sense.
>> Fantastic. We're out of time guys.
Again, this was a fantastic lecture. I'm
sure we have lots of questions. Uh but
uh we'll thank Omar for his time and
everybody give him a hand. Uh this was
amazing. It's false.